Carolyn Jane Anderson

650 North Pleasant Street University of Massachusetts Amherst, MA 01003

Email: carolynander@umass.edu Web: http://candersl.github.io

Research Focus

My research focuses on context-sensitive expressions: words whose meanings change depending on who is speaking to whom, and where. These aspects of language are some of the most challenging for artificial intelligence to grasp, because they are situational, grounded, and interactive. Exploring these questions can help us understand general cognitive behavior such as theory of mind (our beliefs about other people's mental states), and help artificial intelligence learn to use language in a dynamic, responsive way.

Education

Ph.D. in Linguistics. University of Massachusetts, Amherst Dissertation: Shifting the Perspectival Landscape Advisors: Brian Dillon and Rajesh Bhatt M.A. in Linguistics. University of Massachusetts, Amherst

May 2019

June 2020

B.A. in Linguistics and minor in Computer Science. Swarthmore College High Honors in Linguistics and Natural Language Models

June 2014

Positions

Wellesley College, Computer Science Department Assistant professor

Starting Fall 2021

BBN Technologies, Analytics and Machine Intelligence (Cambridge, MA) Research Intern

June 2018-August 2019

- Multi-dialect recurrent neural network language models for ASR
- Masked neural language model prediction for acoustic model rescoring
 Neural machine translation for post-processing numerical terms in ASR
 Statistical analysis of keyword search performance

Fulbright Canada, University of Victoria and McGill University

Fulbright Research Fellow, supervised by Leslie Saxon and Jessica Coon

Topic: Technology in First Nations Language Revitalization

September 2014-May 2015

Cornell University, Computer Science Department (Ithaca, NY)

Research Intern, supervised by Nate Foster

Topic: NetKAT: a domain-specific language for networking

May 2013-August 2013

Funding

BBN Technologies Research Fellowship

Spring 2019 and Spring 2020

Selkirk Linguistics Outreach Fund Award

2016

University of Massachusetts Amherst Fellowship

2015-2016

Fulbright Canada Research Scholarship	2014-2015
Programming Languages Mentoring Workshop Scholarship	2013 and 2014
Marianne Durand Frey '57 Scholar	2011-2014
National Merit Scholar	2010

Publications

- 1. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. *Tomorrow* is not always a day away. *Proceedings of Sinn und Bedeutung* (SuB) 23, 2019. **Selected for oral presentation**.
- 2. Anderson, Carolyn Jane and Brian Dillon. Guess who's coming (and who's going): bringing perspective to the Rational Speech Acts framework. *Proceedings of the Society for Computation in Linguistics* (SCiL), 2019.
- 3. Anderson, Carolyn Jane and Brook Danielle Lillehaugen. 2016. Negation in Colonial Valley Zapotec. *Transactions of the Philological Society* 114(3).
- Anderson, Carolyn Jane, Nate Foster, Arjun Guha, Jean-Baptiste Jeannin, Dexter Kozen, Cole Schlesinger, and David Walker. NetKAT: Semantic foundations for networks. ACM SIGPLAN-SIGACT Symposium on Principles of Programming Languages (POPL), 2014. Selected for oral presentation.

Conference Presentations

- 1. Anderson, Carolyn Jane and Tessa Patapoutian. Can neural network language models understand spatial perspective? Poster presented at the Bridging AI and Cognitive Science (BAICS) workshop, at the International Conference on Learning Representations (ICLR), 2020.
- 2. Anderson, Carolyn Jane and Brian Dillon. Taking other perspectives into account: an RSA model of perspectival reasoning. Talk given at Rational Approaches in Language Science (RAiLS), 2019.
- 3. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. Explaining the progressive motion verb puzzle in Zapotec. Talk given at the Texas Linguistics Society, 2019.
- 4. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. *Tomorrow* isn't always a day away. Poster presented at the 31st annual CUNY Human Sentence Processing Conference, 2018.
- 5. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. The San Lucas Quiaviní Zapotec andative and venitive. Talk presented at the Society for the Study of Indigenous Languages of the Americas (SSILA) annual meeting, 2018. **Honorable Mention, Best Student Paper Presentation**
- Anderson, Carolyn Jane. The andative and venitive construction in San Lucas Quiaviní Zapotec. Talk presented at Multi-Verb Constructions: Semantic, Syntactic and Typological Perspectives (MVC), 2017.
- 7. Anderson, Carolyn Jane and Brook Danielle Lillehaugen. The morphosyntax of negation in Colonial Valley Zapotec. Talk presented at the Society for the Study of Indigenous Languages of the Americas (SSILA) annual meeting, 2015.
- 8. Anderson, Carolyn Jane and Brook Danielle Lillehaugen. La morfosintaxis de la negation en el zapoteco del Valle colonial. Talk presented at Coloquio sobre Lenguas Otomangues y Vecinas (COLOV) IV: Mario Molina Cruz, 2014.
- 9. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. Language ideology and human rights doctrine in Morocco. Talk presented at New Ways of Analyzing Variation (NWAV) 42, 2013.

Manuscripts

- 1. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. 2019. Tomorrow isn't always a day away: Non-utterance time readings of *tomorrow*. Under revision.
- 2. Anderson, Carolyn Jane and Brian Dillon. 2019. Taking other perspectives into account: modeling the use of perspectival expressions in discourse. Ms., University of Massachusetts, Amherst.
- 3. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. 2017. The andative and venitive construction in San Lucas Quiaviní Zapotec. Ms., University of Massachusetts, Amherst.
- 4. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. 2014. I talk it and I feel it: Language attitudes of Moroccan university students. Honors thesis, Swarthmore College.

Invited Talks

- 1. Cornell Tech, Department of Computer Science. 'Guess Who's Coming to Dinner: a Bayesian approach to modeling perspective." 2020.
- 2. Boston University, Department of Linguistics. "Guess Who's Coming to Dinner: a Bayesian approach to modeling perspective." 2019.
- 3. Colgate University, Department of Computer Science. "Guess Who's Coming to Dinner: a Bayesian approach to modeling perspective." 2019.
- 4. Denison University, Department of Data Analytics. "Guess Who's Coming to Dinner: a Bayesian approach to modeling perspective." 2019.
- 5. James Madison University, Department of Computer Science. "Guess Who's Coming to Dinner: a Bayesian approach to modeling perspective." 2019.
- 6. Mount Holyoke College, Department of Computer Science. "Guess Who's Coming to Dinner: a Bayesian approach to modeling perspective." 2019.
- 7. Occidental College, Department of Computer Science. "Guess Who's Coming to Dinner: a Bayesian approach to modeling perspective." 2019.
- 8. University of Massachusetts, Amherst, Department of Computer Science. "Guess Who's Coming to Dinner: a Bayesian approach to modeling perspective." 2019.
- 9. Wellesley College, Department of Computer Science. "Guess Who's Coming to Dinner: a Bayesian approach to modeling perspective." 2019.

Other Presentations

- 1. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. Reasoning about perspectives. Abstract selected for presentation at the Science Speed Geeking event at the XPrag Summer School, 2019.
- 2. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. Use your words (better): two projects on making better use of text for ASR. Intern presentation, BBN Technologies, 2019.
- 3. Anderson, Carolyn Jane. Neural networks for ASR: focusing on the text. Intern presentation, BBN Technologies, 2018.

Teaching

reaching	
1. Instructor, University of Massachusetts Amherst, Linguistics Department First Year Seminar: Technology for Language Revitalization	Fall 2019
 Teaching Assistant, University of Massachusetts Amherst, Linguistics Depar Language Processing and the Brain (Instructor: Brian Dillon) 	rtment Fall 2019
 Instructor, Mt. Holyoke College, Computer Science Department Programming Languages 	Fall 2018
 Teaching Assistant, University of Massachusetts Amherst, Linguistics Depar Introduction to Linguistic Theory (Instructor: Seth Cable) 	tment Spring 2017
 Teaching Assistant, University of Massachusetts Amherst, Linguistics Depar Cognitive Modeling (Instructor: Gaja Jarosz) 	tment Fall 2017
Advising	
Undergraduate Research Assistants	
Tessa Patapoutian Project: experimental and computational modeling of perspectival motion verbs	Spring 2019-present
Alicia LeClair Project: Perspectival motion verbs in Western Tlacolula Valley Zapotec	Spring 2017
Awards	
Computing Research Association Outstanding Undergraduate Researchers Award	l Finalist 2014
The Linguistics Prize in Applications of Theory, Swarthmore College	2014
Phi Beta Kappa Inductee	2014
Philip M. Hicks Prize for Best Critical Essay	2013
Research Assistantships	
University of Massachusetts Amherst, Linguistics Department Research Assistant Primary investigator: Seth Cable Topic: Semantics of Endangered Languages in North America	Spring 2017
University of Massachusetts Amherst, Linguistics Department Research Assistant Primary investigator: Gaja Jarosz Topic: Computational phonology	Fall 2016
Haverford College, Ticha Digital Humanities Project (Haverford, PA) Research Intern Advisor: Brook Lillehaugen Topic: Web-based preservation and presentation of Colonial Valley Zapotec texts	June 2014–August 2014

4

Service

Organizer: Neural Networks in Linguistics Reading Group

Graduate Representative to Faculty Meetings

2016–2017

Skype A Scientist Volunteer

Spring 2020

Skills

Natural Languages

- Bangla (novice)
- French (advanced)
- German (intermediate)
- Modern Standard Arabic (intermediate)
- Spanish (intermediate)
- Western Tlacolula Valley Zapotec (fieldwork)

Domain Specific Languages

- Tensorflow (intermediate)
- WebPPL (intermediate)

Programming Languages

- C++ (novice)
- Coq (intermediate)
- Figaro (intermediate)
- Haskell (novice)
- Java (intermediate)
- JavaScript (intermediate)
- Python (advanced)
- R (advanced)
- Racket (advanced)

References

Brian Dillon

Department of Linguistics, University of Massachusetts, Amherst (brian@linguist.umass.edu)

Rajesh Bhatt

Department of Linguistics, University of Massachusetts, Amherst (bhatt@linguist.umass.edu)

Daniel Altshuler

School of Cognitive Science, Hampshire College (dgaCS@hampshire.edu)

Matthew Snover

Artificial and Machine Intelligence, BBN Technologies (matt.snover@raytheon.com)